<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Uncategorized | Charles Hooper]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/categories/uncategorized/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-19T12:53:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charles Hooper]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Validating Data with New-Style Classes in Python]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/validating-data-with-new-style-classes-in-python/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/validating-data-with-new-style-classes-in-python</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>Every once in awhile in my reading I come across a minor reference to what pythonistas refer to as <strong>new-style classes</strong>. One of the nice things about new-style classes is the `property` decorators. These property decorators allow you to build getter and setter methods to access object attributes. This is pretty awesome because now you can perform validation at the model/class level whenever you assign a value to a property of an object.</p>

<p>e.g., In one of my projects, I have an attribute named <em>timestamp</em> that takes a `datetime` object. I was concerned about receiving incorrect types from my input because there are alot of ways a programmer can represent the concept of time. Some realistic possibilities of invalid types in my case are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>`time` objects from the time module</li>
  <li>`string` objects that contain the date and time (and various possible formats)</li>
  <li>`float` or `int` objects that contain a unix timestamp</li>
</ul>

<p>With a setter method, you can test that the new value being assigned to an attribute is the correct type before assigning it. You can also throw an <strong>exception</strong> if it’s not. In other words, you can do something like this:</p>

<pre><code>from datetime import datetime

class SomeObject(object):    # new-style classes must be subclassed from object
    _timestamp = None

    @property
    def timestamp(self):
        return self._timestamp

    @timestamp.setter    # the prefix must match the read-only getter func name
    def timestamp(self,value):    # the func name must match the read-only getter func name
        if not isinstance(value, datetime):
            raise ValueError(“Timestamp can only be an instance of Datetime”)
        self._timestamp = value
</code></pre>

<p>Go ahead and try it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three Reasons Why I&#8217;m Ditching ChunkHost]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/three-reasons-why-im-ditching-chunkhost/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/three-reasons-why-im-ditching-chunkhost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>I’ve been using <a href="http://chunkhost.com/r/chdotnet">ChunkHost</a> for the past <strong>eight months</strong> to host my website and some minor web applications. After my short, free “beta” period I was given a 30% discount (forever) and billed like a normal customer. I’ve only had to pay <strong>$13.30</strong> a month for a Xen VPS with <strong>512MB RAM</strong>. This used to be pretty competitive <a href="http://blog.linode.com/2010/06/16/linode-turns-7-big-ram-increase/">until Linode increased the RAM for all of their VPS packages</a>. Unfortunately for ChunkHost, this Linode RAM increase and some recent events have persuaded me to <a href="http://www.linode.com/?r=2fce38a23c4154c3a1abb4f99aafd6371ee78ecc"><strong>pay the extra 7 bucks to Linode</strong></a>. Here are the three main reasons why I’m ditching ChunkHost:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>No way to give feedback on the service.</strong> First, let me qualify this and say that there <em>is</em> a “Feedback” button on the site. However, more than a quick cursory glance reveals that their feedback system is <strong>inactive **and **neglected</strong>. For example, I have an eight month old feature request that has gone ignored; not rejected, not WONTFIX’d, but ignored. Other customers have older feature requests that have been promised “shortly” and never delivered.<img src="http://cdn.subversity.net/blog_imgs/chunkhost-inactive.png" alt="An example of ChunkHost's inactive GetSatisfaction feedback page" title="chunkhost-inactive.png" /> 
  
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p><strong>There is no SLA (service-level agreement) or uptime guarantee.</strong> Recently, I noticed that my VM was down and the main page for ChunkHost was down as well. I emailed support about the outage and was happy to receive a quick reply.<br />
&gt; Yeah, we’re looking at it now; it looks like networking oddness on one of the host machines. We’ll update Twitter with info as we have it!</p>

        <p>The “fix” consisted of ChunkHost <strong>rebooting the physical host</strong> my VM was on. This same problem occurred *again <strong>*5 hours later</strong>. I don’t sense any empathy from ChunkHost for bearing with them through their downtime and I certainly haven’t received any type of apology. Am I entitled to one? With the lack of an SLA, maybe not, but I’d be alot less bitter and I might have remained a customer had I received one.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><strong>Not enough notice given for “scheduled” maintenance.</strong> Four days before the two outages I had experienced, ChunkHost performed some scheduled maintenance. I am thankful that the maintenance occurred in off-peak hours, but <strong>I received the notice at the end of the previous day</strong>. This is not adequate notice. Had there been anything critical running on my VM, I would expect adequate notice so I could make proper arrangements ahead of time. 
It saddens me to think that my last eight months at ChunkHost were a waste. Fortunately, <a href="http://www.linode.com/?r=2fce38a23c4154c3a1abb4f99aafd6371ee78ecc">I’ve been using Linode for my “real services” for just as long</a> and I know that I won’t be disappointed there. If you’re looking for a VM for testing and development purposes only, ChunkHost might be an option – just don’t let your development server evolve into a production server.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I think and think for months and years. 99 times, the conclusion is false. The hundredth time I am right &#8211; Einstein]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/i-think-and-think-for-months-and-years-99-times-the-conclusion-is-false-the-hundredth-time-i-am-right-einstein/
/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/i-think-and-think-for-months-and-years-99-times-the-conclusion-is-false-the-hundredth-time-i-am-right-einstein/i-think-and-think-for-months-and-years-99-times-the-conclusion-is-false-the-hundredth-time-i-am-right-einstein</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>“I think and think for months and years. Ninety-nine times, the conclusion is false. The hundredth time I am right.” — <a href="http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1921/einstein-bio.html">Albert Einstein</a></p>

<p>I think Einstein was onto the <a href="http://www.sebastianmarshall.com/?p=195">equal-odds rule</a>.  </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The HN Effect in Numbers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/the-hn-effect-in-numbers/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/the-hn-effect-in-numbers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>For the unfamiliar, I wrote an article about a week and a half ago titled <a href="http://blog.charleshooper.net/how-i-made-money-spamming-twitter-with-contex">How I Made Money Spamming Twitter with Contextual Book Suggestions</a> and promised that I would follow up with a post on the type of traffic I received. Not only did the article get to be pretty popular with the <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/">Hacker News</a> crowd, republished in <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/sai">Silicon Alley Insider</a>, and make me the recipient of a handful of wonderful emails but I even got to visit <a href="http://www.tracked.com/">tracked.com’s engineering team</a> and get schooled on machine learning techniques and A.I. (hi guys!) 
Something relevant I should mention is that, just a day before, I had migrated my <a href="http://posterous.com">Posterous</a> blog from one domain to its current place, <a href="http://blog.charleshooper.net">blog.charleshooper.net</a>. To anyone who’s curious, this was a totally painless process. Set up DNS first, update your Posterous settings, and set up 302 redirects so your links don’t break. 
<strong>Social Link-Sharing</strong><br />
Despite finishing my article at 1:00 AM, I thought it was pretty well-written and I wanted my story to be heard, so I decided to get a full night’s sleep, proof-read it in the morning, and submit the link to Reddit, Digg, and Hacker News. Besides the obvious benefits of proof-reading the article while fully-rested, I also recognized that most link-sharing sites weight votes based on time (or rather, some product of votes/time maybe) so submitting my article in the morning meant that it would first show up at the beginning of what I believe to be peak usage. So how’d I do? 
Reddit hated it.<br />
<img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Digg didn’t care.<br />
<img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_2.png" alt="" /> 
And Hacker News loved it!<br />
<img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_4.png" alt="" /> 
I also make use of Posterous’ “autopost” features and have all my new submissions get posted to Twitter and Facebook. According to Posterous, there were over 77 retweets of my article (most likely from the tweet storm that the Silicon Alley Insider bot and HN bots started) and 7 “likes” on Facebook. 
<strong>Traffic</strong><br />
According to Google Analytics, I’m not very popular. Before publishing my article, I received an average of about 30 visits a day. On the day I published my article, I observed a surge of over 4,600 visitors. From there, the numbers declined daily at a rate that looks very much like exponential decay. It took 10 days for my traffic to return to normal, but that day was a Sunday and the following Monday was almost twice as high (62 visits). For the number geeks, the set of numbers beginning with the peak is (4652, 2688, 1065, 452, 206, 138, 105). I got close with the expression <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=graph f(x) = 4652e^(-0.6x); x from 0 to 6"><em>f(x) = 4652e^(-0.6x)</em></a> but that isn’t quite right (maybe I should treat my average visits as a constant.) 
Update: I’ve gotten much closer with <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=table[ 2658e^(-0.94x) %2B 30, {x,0,5} ]">f(x) = 2658e^(-0.94x) 30</a></p>

<p><img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_6-300x168.png" alt="" /> </p>

<p>Over the time period, my article received over 9,000 unique page views with a bounce rate of over 90% (~93% exit rate.) I remember reading an article a little while ago that stated, on single-page use cases, the bounce rate will always be close to the exit rate unless the analytics software “phones in” after some period of time to register the visit as something other than a bounce. I use Google Analytics and, unless I find out otherwise, I don’t think it does this (although, it does measure “time on page” so maybe it does and Google’s idea of a bounce is different than mine.) </p>

<p><img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_7.png" alt="" /><br />
 <strong>Sources</strong><br />
My largest source of traffic was referring websites making up over 70% of it. Less than 2% was from search engines and I don’t even think that any of it was destined for my article. 
<img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_9.png" alt="" /><br />
 As for the referring websites, I received traffic from all over. However, most of it was from <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/">Hacker News</a>, <a href="http://TechMeme.com">TechMeme.com</a>, and <a href="http://Google.com">Google.com</a>. I looked into “<a href="http://google.com">google.com</a> / referral” versus “<a href="http://google.com">google.com</a> / organic” and the referrals mostly consisted of visitors using Google Reader. What isn’t shown below is the 113 <em>other</em> referring sites. The “<a href="http://daemonology.net">daemonology.net</a>” referral is a result of <a href="http://www.daemonology.net/hn-daily/">HN Daily</a>. As you can see, my top sources are primarily seeded by social media and social link-sharing websites. 
<img src="http://www.charleshooper.net/wp-content/uploads/Picture_8-300x198.png" alt="" /><br />
 <strong>Conclusion</strong><br />
To conclude, don’t under-value the social sites. If you want some organic link juice then utilize the “chatty” sites like Facebook and Twitter as well as the link-sharing sites such as Hacker News, Reddit, and Digg. There is a hidden benefit to putting yourself out there and asking for alot of attention: You will ensure that your articles, blog posts, and research are high-quality resources of <em>useful</em> information. Essentially, you end up treating each blog post as you would any startup. Experiment first. Create value second. The rest (profit, respect, esteem) comes easy.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New URL/Domain for my Blog (formerly subversity.net)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/new-urldomain-for-my-blog-formerly-subversity-net/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/new-urldomain-for-my-blog-formerly-subversity-net</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>As I stand before you sipping my celebratory <a href="http://beeradvocate.com/beer/profile/220/56613">Wilco Tango Foxtrot</a>, I would like to present to you <a href="http://blog.charleshooper.net/">the new home for my blog</a>. The reason for this migration is that I am downsizing the amount of under-utilized domains I renew each year. Please update your bookmarks accordingly :-)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
