<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Charles Hooper]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-28T13:52:08-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charles Hooper]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Give it a rest]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/give-it-a-rest/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-03T18:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/give-it-a-rest</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8649/16189710525_1191b9eb7f_z_d.jpg" alt="Dying zucchini (courgette)" /></p>

<p>Yesterday I walked out to my yard to find that all of my zucchini
(courgette) plants are dying. It was cold enough the night before to
kill them all at once and there really isn’t any saving them.</p>

<p>We got greedy at first and wanted to reclaim the wasted space, until we
realized that our garden has been running strong for about 9 months now,
since Erica and I planted our first seeds of the season in March of last
year. Now we’ve decided to give it a rest so we can add some new compost to
fortify the soil.</p>

<p>For me, the dying zucchini plants serve as a reminder that nature
intends for us to rest and will find a way to see that we do (sometimes
permanently). Plants drop seed, decompose, and ultimately end up feeding
their offspring. Animals need to eat and sleep.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7541/15568029134_2263d267b9_z_d.jpg" alt="Caesar not sleeping" /></p>

<p>It’s a new year and you likely just had some time off that wasn’t very
restful. If you’re like me, you were probably busy traveling, shopping,
worrying about money, or the holidays may even open up some new wounds
for you. Don’t accept this as your vacation for the year.</p>

<p>Your real vacation should be about rest and relaxation. You can travel
or you can stay home, but the bottom line is that you should be
relaxing. Sleep in some days if you’d like. When you’re awake, maybe
read a book, go for a walk, or take up that hobby you’ve been thinking
about. On my last stay-cation, I tried our archery for the first time
and have been hooked ever since.</p>

<p>So start planning your time off now. Trust me, it’s worth it.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7542/15570698153_05774d7eb9_z_d.jpg" alt="First archery target" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Do as an SRE]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/what-i-do-sre/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T06:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/what-i-do-as-an-sre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>Sometimes people ask me what I do and I’m not really sure how to answer
them. My answer tends to depend on social setting, what I’ve been
working on, and if I was on call that week. No matter the circumstances,
it usually comes out pretty boring and terribly short.</p>

<p>This really sucks though, because I actually really <em>like</em> my job and
think that it’s interesting, if only I could articulate it.</p>

<p>So here’s some attempt at explaining what I do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>I’m an SRE, or <em>Service Reliability Engineer</em>,
at <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>. Typically, SRE stands for <em>Site</em>
Reliability Engineer, however we’ve modernized it at Heroku because what
is even a site anymore?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My week-to-week is wildly unpredictable. This week I’m conducting an
operational review of one of our key platform components, last week I
was investigating and addressing database bloat, and the week before I
was the on-call incident commander and quite busy due to several
incidents that occurred.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Speaking of the incident commander role, part of my job includes
<em>defining</em> how we respond to incidents. At first glance it seems easy:
Get paged and show up. And then you respond to your first 24-hour
slow-burning incident and realize that you’ve got more work to do.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Following incidents, I also schedule and faciliate retrospectives. We
practice <a href="http://codeascraft.com/2012/05/22/blameless-postmortems/">blameless
postmortems</a>
and these tend to be incredibly constructive.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I also analyze past incident data and look for patterns and trends.
Wondering if there’s a day of week that has a higher probability of
experiencing an incident? Yeah, it’s Friday.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When all is quiet, I review dashboards and investigate anomolies.
Wondering what that weird spike or dip is that seems to happen every
once in a while? Ask me, I’ve probably pulled that thread before (and if
I haven’t, I’ll be terribly curious).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>And sometimes I build integration tests and tools. I wrote
<a href="/blog/troubleshooting-elbs-with-elbping/">elbping</a>, for instance,
because ELBs were terrible to troubleshoot during an incident.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>And, most importantly, I mentor other SREs and software engineers.
This is the single biggest thing I can do in terms of its impact, and
probably most rewarding, too.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>So there you have it, that’s what I do.</p>

<p>P.S. - If this sounds interesting to you, <a href="http://jobs.heroku.com/">we’re hiring</a>!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I moved to San Francisco]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/why-i-moved-to-san-francisco/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-21T00:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/why-i-moved-to-san-francisco</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>It’s been three months since I first moved to San Francisco and decided
I should share why I moved here in the first place. The primary reasons
why I moved to San Francisco are for my career and to be around more
like-minded people.</p>

<p>Career-wise, what made San Francisco appealing to me is the number and
diversity of employment opportunities. In Connecticut, if you want to
work with “technology” then you work for one of the many insurance
companies headquartered there or an agency of some kind. In addition to
available opportunities, there is also more parity between the job
market in the bay area and my skill set and experience. For example,
today <a href="http://www.indeed.com/">Indeed.com</a> reports 184 results for the “Python” in the entire
state of Connecticut, while there are nearly 2,700 results for the San
Francisco Bay Area. At one point in my life, I was told I was wasting my
life messing around with GNU/Linux and other Open Source software.
Things would have been a little better if I moved two hours away to
either Boston or New York, but if I’m going to move then I might as well
get better weather out of it, too.</p>

<p>I also moved to San Francisco to be around more like-minded people.
Things that interest me (besides gardening and home brewing) are
startups and tech. There were a few groups around my old location that
were interesting, but they typically required an hour long drive to show
up to their events. Often times, the groups failed early due to a lack
of participation (including the hackerspace I founded but that story is
for another day).</p>

<h2 id="thoughts-so-far">Thoughts so far</h2>

<p>As I mentioned, I’ve now been here for three months. My thoughts so far
are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The place really is quite small. Especially in tech. Everyone seems to
know everyone, which can be fun socially, but you need to watch what
you say when you’re talking shop.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Sillicon Valley/SF Bay tech isolation chamber is real (and so is
the echo chamber). Companies sometimes seem huge when you’re in the
bay, but if you talk to anyone from outside of the area, they’re like
“<em>Who?</em>”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>San Francisco’s neighborhoods are really awesome. SF
is divided into a bunch of small neighborhoods, each with their own
unique attributes. There really is a place for everyone.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I moved to San Francisco because I thought it would be good for my
career and because I thought I would meet more like-minded people. This
has certainly proved to be the case. What I was not expecting but have
experienced so far is how small and isolated the SF tech scene actually
is.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Hacked My High School]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/how-i-hacked-my-high-school/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-18T10:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/how-i-hacked-my-high-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>When I was a freshman or sophomore in high school, I cracked my high
school and got in “a lot of trouble” for it. I’ve only told the story
maybe half a dozen times in my life, but after telling it a few times in
the past month or so, I decided to write about.</p>

<p>I went to a high school in a fairly decent school district that
apparently had enough money to build several computer labs in each
school, network them all together as a single autonomous network, and
provide reasonably fast Internet access. This was somewhere between the
year 1999 and the year 2000, the exact year I can’t quite remember.</p>

<p>Another interesting thing to note about my high school was that it
carried with it an 80-hour community service requirement for graduation.
I’ve always been into computers and networking
so it was natural for me volunteer to do my community service assisting
the technical staff in the computer labs. Community service in this way
typically involved installing printer drivers, updating software, and
pushing boxes around on a cart.</p>

<p>My school’s computer network consisted of a mix of sevaral flavors of
Windows including Windows 95, Windows 98, and Windows NT 4.0. Despite
the large Microsoft-only network, we were using Novell for
authentication and authorization. Each school in the district was
networked together and part of this same Novell network.</p>

<p>My school had reasonable filtering and monitoring in place for web
traffic and it wasn’t uncommon to hear of students getting into trouble
for looking at, let’s say “questionable content.”</p>

<p>One weird thing my school did was restrict access to the local hard
drive. If you went into Explorer, the <code>C:\</code> volume simply wasn’t listed.
This was supposedly because we were supposed to use our network-attached
“S drive” which was unique to each user. The “Run” dialog from the Start
menu was also disabled.</p>

<p>This had its flaws; however, and one day I hand-wrote (in English class)
a 6 page paper detailing the variety of ways even an unskilled person
could bypass this precaution. Most notably this included:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Create a shortcut on the desktop to <code>C:\</code></li>
  <li>Open internet explorer and browse to <code>file:///...</code></li>
  <li>Certain “Save As” and “Open” dialogs still listed the C-drive and was browsable</li>
  <li>You could still get to a “Run” dialog by opening the task manager and finding it in there. This allowed you to a) Browse to the C-drive anyway, and b) Open up a command prompt</li>
</ul>

<p>There were probably some other flaws I missed. I argued that restricting
access to the local disk was rather pointless as people could simply
drop to it during boot (which many students were already doing in order
to get a kick out of doing <code>deltree C:\Windows</code> for some reason) and
that the real issue was that local password caching was enabled. In
other words, whenever a user logged in, a hashed version of their
password was stored in the form of a windows “PWL file.”</p>

<p>The next time I did my community service, I handed my paper to the head
technician which he responded “What? This could never happen”
and threw my paper in the garbage.</p>

<p>What?! I couldn’t believe that someone would actually throw away what
was, at the time, the longest paper I’ve ever written after barely
having read it. And to do this with a 4-word response no less!</p>

<p>Due to my shock and what was apparent lack of maturity, I decided
that I would show them. I mean, when you approach someone with what you
think is an obvious, logical opinion and they don’t believe you, your
next option is to show them, right? <em>Right?</em></p>

<p>It didn’t take me too long to gather up a fairly large collection of
these so-called “PWL files” on a floppy disk. Distinguishing between
staff and students was trivial too due to the naming convention in
place. Students’ usernames were always in the form of
<code>{ExpectedGraduationYear}{LastName}{FirstInitial}</code>. Mine was
<code>03hooperc</code>. Faculty and staff, on the other hand, simply followed the
convention <code>{FirstInitial}{LastName}</code>. I decided that I didn’t care for
any of the student logins and just discarded them.</p>

<p>When I had a good collection of staff PWL files, I used a tool called
<a href="http://www.oxid.it/cain.html">Cain &amp; Abel</a> on my home computer and ran it overnight.</p>

<p>In the morning, I was surprised to see how many passwords were cracked.
Among them, one staff login stuck out at me. It was the technician who
threw my paper out. I knew that because, unlike the rest of the
technical staff, he mostly worked on network issues, he must have alot
more access than anyone else. His password was hilariously bad and
insecure. It consisted of two three-letter words in all caps:</p>

<pre><code>THEMAN
</code></pre>

<p>The man, huh? I giggled and went to school ready to launch my next
attack. I went to the computer lab during lunch and waited for the
opportunity to log into my new staff account. I had to be careful,
though, as my school set the background of staff accounts to something
very noticable and I didn’t want the computer lab attendant sitting in
the back to notice that I was on an account that didn’t belong to me. At
some point, she left briefly and I quickly logged onto The Man’s
account.</p>

<p>Once I was logged in, I was more in excited and nervous than
anything. Even still, I moved onto the next step of creating a backdoor
account with admin privileges. I made up a name and created a new
account following the faculty/staff naming convention and granted it
every privilege I could. As soon as I was done, I logged off. The
log-off couldn’t be slower. I felt like Peter in Office Space when he’s
trying to duck out of work early and his computer keeps coming up with
a bunch of last-minute tasks before it can log off.</p>

<p>I logged into my backdoor account exactly once to verify that it worked
and never logged into it again. I fucked up and made the classic mistake
of telling a friend. He was one of the few people I knew who also used
Linux and we used to trade books, CDs, and manuals all the time. My
favorite trade was giving him <a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/6527">Debian GNU/Linux: Guide to Installation and Usage</a>
for a manual from Bell Canada about this crazy thing called SONET and
T-carrier transmission systems (e.g., T-1 lines). Who knew that I would
one day work for an ISP and later move on to manage thousands of Linux
hosts based on a Debian derivative?</p>

<p>Some months later, I start hearing from other students that my buddy has
told a bunch of people my secret and has even been logging into the
account to prove it (OK, I definitely shouldn’t have shared the
credentials!) I decided that the best thing to do in this case was to
confess to the Director of Information Technology, who I used to bug
from time to time and ask why we didn’t use Linux since it’s free (Yes,
I was probably a very annoying fifteen year old) For those wondering, he
said it was because of a “licensing issue” which I think was
professional speak for “fuck off, kid”). So, I walked into his office
one day and dropped the bomb.</p>

<p>I honestly don’t know what I was expecting to happen. He listened to my
story, asked me how long I had this access for. When I told him, he
remarked that their backups didn’t back that far and that, in any case,
he’d have to report me to the administration. He walked me over to the
dean of disclipline’s office and I went through a grueling session of
more questions.</p>

<p>Something I should probably note is that this during a period where a
bunch of schools, including mine, had decided to institute a
so-called “zero tolerance policy.” What these zero-tolerance policies
were was simply a matrix of “Violations” on one axis and
“Number of prior offenses” on the other. In other words, getting caught
smoking in the bathroom for the first time carried a pre-determined
penalty which was slightly less bad than getting caught doing that for
the second time. Students could never argue that they didn’t know they
would get in so much trouble for anything because this matrix and every
other school/district policy was distributed to us at the beginning of
the year and we were required to have it on us at all times.</p>

<p>The obvious flaw with this policy, besides the fact that it ignores
additional circumstances, is that in 1999 there wasn’t a row describing
the penalties for any of the things I had done. In fact, I hadn’t
technically violated any of the school or district policies at all!
(Federal and local crimes may be another issue). I was sent home with
the dean of discipline still deciding what to do with me, but I figured
I was probably going to be suspended for a few days.</p>

<p>I went home and told my parents what happened and, very very <em>very</em>
surprisingly, they said I did the right thing (albeit many months late).
Something else amazing happened though. My parents called the school
and, after talking to the dean, we learned that my school was actually
considering <strong>expulsion!</strong> My parents made some phone calls and tried to
pull some strings that we didn’t think we had but ultimately told me that
we wouldn’t know my fate until the next day at school.</p>

<p>The next day I went into school and was immediately called into the
dean’s office. He explained that they had decided that what I was guilty
of stealing and kept using this “stole the key to the bank” metaphor. He
actually told me that had I not brought the password files home on a
floppy disk, I would probably be in less trouble. What the fuck?</p>

<p>And then I received my sentencing: Ten day suspension.</p>

<p>Ten days! That was <em>huge</em>. For comparison:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ten days in the maximum amount of time you could be suspended for. Anything longer would be considered an expulsion and would require a hearing of some kind.</li>
  <li>You could punch someone in the face (you know, assault) and the punishment for doing that would be 4-6 days… on the second offense.</li>
</ul>

<p>I don’t remember how I got home but it was like my parents weren’t even
mad. In fact, they seemed more proud than anything. I think they even
thought that this incident would get me hired somewhere someday, too.</p>

<p>After my suspension, I returned to school to learn that, in addition to
my now-served suspension, I was no longer allowed to use any of the
computers at school. This lasted over a year and, after signing a paper
agreeing to let my school sue me if I commit another offence, I was
given my computer access back.</p>

<p>I’m terrible at concluding stories so… The End.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Catching up]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/catching-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T04:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/catching-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Moved to San Francisco</li>
  <li>Took time off to decompress</li>
  <li>Joined team at Heroku</li>
  <li>Loving it</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="code--verbosecode"><code>--verbose</code></h2>

<p>It’s been a while since I’ve posted, but I wanted to let you know that
I’m still alive! Things were very hectic due to a few life changes but I
much of the dust has settled now and I’m excited to talk about what
those changes are.</p>

<p>But first, some history.</p>

<p>In 2011, I was a junior at university studying Business
Information Systems. I had some prior systems engineering and operations
experience and was paying my tuition by performing contract work for a
company that doesn’t exist today. While at this company, I worked very
closely with a developer and the two of us were responsible for running
this company’s infrastructure. Neither of us had the time or the
willpower to be bothered by operational tasks, so we automated
everything. Even though our environment was much smaller (somewhere
between 30-50 instances in EC2) than many others, we had alot of things
that many companies are lacking:</p>

<ul>
  <li>New services were in configuration management</li>
  <li>New deployments were almost entirely automated</li>
  <li>We had good visibility with a variety of metrics being reported to Ganglia and Graphite</li>
  <li>We even had a reasonable nagios configuration</li>
</ul>

<p>Around this time, the term <strong>devops</strong> was being tossed around on twitter
on a more frequent basis. I can remember actually having a Google Alert
for the term to email me when there were new blog posts about it and it
<em>not</em> being spammy. I have a love/hate relationship with the term, and
in December 2011 I wrote my blog post <a href="/blog/concurrent-engineering-the-foundation-of-devops/">Concurrent Engineering: The
Foundation of DevOps</a> in which I argued that the ideas behind devops
weren’t new, but were maybe old ideas from business that were recently
independtly re-discovered.</p>

<p>The blog post wasn’t very popular, but Solomon Hykes (CEO of dotCloud)
managed to see it and, thinking we had very similar ideas about devops,
invited me to interview for a position on their newly formed Site
Reliability Engineering team. I got the job at dotCloud, and up until
April of this year that’s where I stayed.</p>

<p>In mid-April, I resigned from my position at dotCloud and moved to San
Francisco. There were a number of reasons for the resignation but chief
among them was that I needed some time to decompress and all of my paid
time-off had been used up following my youngest brother’s car accident.
This ended up being an awesome decision because it gave me my
much-needed decompression time and I was able to explore my new city.</p>

<p>I took about four weeks off before I put any real effort towards a job
search. The move to San Francisco and the job search alone could fill
two entirely-too-verbose blog posts but the end result was that I moved
here safely and joined the team at <a href="http://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>!</p>

<p>Fast forward to today and I’ve just finished my third week at Heroku.
It’s an amazing experience, a great team, and an awesome culture that is
encapsulated in the following quote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I like our culture. We welcome failure into our house and then kick
its teeth in.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ll write more about this another time. For now, thank you for
listening to my story.</p>

<p>— Charles</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
