<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Charles Hooper]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-24T08:21:20-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charles Hooper]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Archery FAQ]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/personal-archery-faq/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-24T06:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/personal-archery-faq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p><img class="left" src="https://scontent.fsjc1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/11021236<em>10153134291301703</em>2769454311846845625_n.jpg?oh=8c673907f07dfb96ce3ad11e5a43ab1b&amp;oe=560176B4" width="270" height="480" title="Archery" ></p>

<p>When people learn that I’m a traditional archer, they tend to ask me a number of
questions. I thought this might be a fun blog post, so here we go!</p>

<h2 id="how-far-do-i-shoot">How far do I shoot?</h2>

<p>I don’t shoot very far! Because I’m currently focused on form (more on
that below), I am only shooting from between ten to twenty meters.</p>

<h2 id="how-accurate-am-i">How accurate am I?</h2>

<p>I’m not at all because I’m currently focused on <em>precision</em>. This is
mostly a matter of form and consistency, which is why I don’t have to
“shoot” (“loose”? “let”?) from very far. I can spend an entire session
at 10 meters and get very rapid feedback on this, so I do. (Note: I’m
being pedantic about precision vs accuracy, explanation in the image
below).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://cdn.antarcticglaciers.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/precision_accuracy.png" width="417" height="278" title="“Precision vs Accuracy”" ></p>

<p>A variation of this question is sometimes if I’ve ever “robin hooded” an
arrow. <em>Robin hooding</em> is when you shoot one arrow back into another
one.</p>

<p><img src="https://scontent.fsjc1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xaf1/v/t1.0-9/11081355_10153196646961703_930555660984900106_n.jpg?oh=44502f240ac9e784ea060ce2d0e06adc&amp;oe=55FFC92E" alt="Not yet - arrow damage" /></p>

<p>My answer today is “not yet!”</p>

<h2 id="have-you-seen-the-video-of-that-danish-guy-lars-something-its-really-amazing">Have you seen the video of that Danish guy? Lars something? It’s really amazing!</h2>

<p>Ah yes, Lars Anderson. He’s done <a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=lars+anderson">a couple of
videos</a> but
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BEG-ly9tQGk">one in particular</a> has
gotten a lot of attention recently.</p>

<p>The videos are pretty amazing to watch and highly entertaining, but you
won’t find me doing those things any time soon. I’m perfectly content
right here.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="https://scontent.fsjc1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/11209693<em>10153295331296703</em>5424043068009224924_n.jpg?oh=9a0a04c3728c5ed68e5efa6708708160&amp;oe=56035DA8" width="270" height="480" title="“Archery point of view”" ></p>

<h2 id="where-do-i-go">Where do I go?</h2>

<p>There’s an <a href="http://www.golden-gate-park.com/archery.html">archery range in Golden Gate
Park</a> which is free to
use. Nearby is the <a href="http://www.bysel.com/sfarch/">San Francisco Archery Pro
Shop</a> which has good lessons and cheap
all-day rentals.</p>

<h2 id="how-did-i-get-started">How did I get started?</h2>

<p>I had been interested in archery for several years but it wasn’t until a
couple of months ago that I finally tried it.</p>

<p>I went to a <a href="http://www.bysel.com/sfarch/">local shop</a> and took my first
lesson. It was so much fun that I took another one and, when I tried to
sign up for my third, my instructor suggested that I should make some
time to practice all of the things I’ve just learned on my own.</p>

<p>So I rented the equipment a few times and eventually just bought my own.</p>

<h2 id="what-did-you-buy">What did you buy?</h2>

<p>I bought a pretty basic recurve bow and everything else I needed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Six arrows</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A quiver</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>An arm guard and glove</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A bow stringer</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Target pins</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>And carrying bag</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>All in all, it cost me about $350.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Give it a rest]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/give-it-a-rest/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-03T18:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/give-it-a-rest</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8649/16189710525_1191b9eb7f_z_d.jpg" alt="Dying zucchini (courgette)" /></p>

<p>Yesterday I walked out to my yard to find that all of my zucchini
(courgette) plants are dying. It was cold enough the night before to
kill them all at once and there really isn’t any saving them.</p>

<p>We got greedy at first and wanted to reclaim the wasted space, until we
realized that our garden has been running strong for about 9 months now,
since Erica and I planted our first seeds of the season in March of last
year. Now we’ve decided to give it a rest so we can add some new compost to
fortify the soil.</p>

<p>For me, the dying zucchini plants serve as a reminder that nature
intends for us to rest and will find a way to see that we do (sometimes
permanently). Plants drop seed, decompose, and ultimately end up feeding
their offspring. Animals need to eat and sleep.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7541/15568029134_2263d267b9_z_d.jpg" alt="Caesar not sleeping" /></p>

<p>It’s a new year and you likely just had some time off that wasn’t very
restful. If you’re like me, you were probably busy traveling, shopping,
worrying about money, or the holidays may even open up some new wounds
for you. Don’t accept this as your vacation for the year.</p>

<p>Your real vacation should be about rest and relaxation. You can travel
or you can stay home, but the bottom line is that you should be
relaxing. Sleep in some days if you’d like. When you’re awake, maybe
read a book, go for a walk, or take up that hobby you’ve been thinking
about. On my last stay-cation, I tried our archery for the first time
and have been hooked ever since.</p>

<p>So start planning your time off now. Trust me, it’s worth it.</p>

<p><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7542/15570698153_05774d7eb9_z_d.jpg" alt="First archery target" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Do as an SRE]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/what-i-do-sre/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T06:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/what-i-do-as-an-sre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>Sometimes people ask me what I do and I’m not really sure how to answer
them. My answer tends to depend on social setting, what I’ve been
working on, and if I was on call that week. No matter the circumstances,
it usually comes out pretty boring and terribly short.</p>

<p>This really sucks though, because I actually really <em>like</em> my job and
think that it’s interesting, if only I could articulate it.</p>

<p>So here’s some attempt at explaining what I do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>I’m an SRE, or <em>Service Reliability Engineer</em>,
at <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>. Typically, SRE stands for <em>Site</em>
Reliability Engineer, however we’ve modernized it at Heroku because what
is even a site anymore?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My week-to-week is wildly unpredictable. This week I’m conducting an
operational review of one of our key platform components, last week I
was investigating and addressing database bloat, and the week before I
was the on-call incident commander and quite busy due to several
incidents that occurred.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Speaking of the incident commander role, part of my job includes
<em>defining</em> how we respond to incidents. At first glance it seems easy:
Get paged and show up. And then you respond to your first 24-hour
slow-burning incident and realize that you’ve got more work to do.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Following incidents, I also schedule and faciliate retrospectives. We
practice <a href="http://codeascraft.com/2012/05/22/blameless-postmortems/">blameless
postmortems</a>
and these tend to be incredibly constructive.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I also analyze past incident data and look for patterns and trends.
Wondering if there’s a day of week that has a higher probability of
experiencing an incident? Yeah, it’s Friday.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When all is quiet, I review dashboards and investigate anomolies.
Wondering what that weird spike or dip is that seems to happen every
once in a while? Ask me, I’ve probably pulled that thread before (and if
I haven’t, I’ll be terribly curious).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>And sometimes I build integration tests and tools. I wrote
<a href="/blog/troubleshooting-elbs-with-elbping/">elbping</a>, for instance,
because ELBs were terrible to troubleshoot during an incident.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>And, most importantly, I mentor other SREs and software engineers.
This is the single biggest thing I can do in terms of its impact, and
probably most rewarding, too.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>So there you have it, that’s what I do.</p>

<p>P.S. - If this sounds interesting to you, <a href="http://jobs.heroku.com/">we’re hiring</a>!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An actual email from a recruiter]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/actual-email-from-recruiter/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-26T09:52:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/actual-emails-from-a-recruiter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>OK, I was going to lead up to this carefully so this didn’t seem like yet
another awful blog post about technical recruiters (can we seriously stop
posting those?) but I have no words. Here is the fifth email sent from one
particular recruiter inside of a week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hey Charles,</p>

  <p>I hope all is well man!  I hadn’t heard back from you after my previous
e-mail so I was toying around with putting together a search party to make
sure you didn’t fall into a well or something.  I’m not sure if that actually
even happens anymore but this dog came up to me on my way to work and was
barking at me in a way that seemed he was attempting to tell me something.</p>

  <p>Naturally, I put two and two together and realized that perhaps I
misunderstood my new furry friend and instead of saying “Chance is in danger”
he said “Charles is in danger”.  Which still doesn’t shed light on the where
abouts of my missing cat Chance, but if you are in fact in danger, don’t
hesitate to let me know.  I can hold my breath for 45 seconds (not that long)
and I can run fast-ish for short distances.  I also have this thing with
blood where I “pass out”.</p>

  <p>On second thought, if your in danger you should probably just call 911 or
yell “fire” (I guess “help” doesn’t work for some reason).  However, if
you’re even remotely interested in discussing the possibility of chatting
about new opportunities, I’m your guy!  Hope to hear from you soon Charles!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yuuuuup.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I moved to San Francisco]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/why-i-moved-to-san-francisco/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-21T00:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.charleshooper.net/blog/why-i-moved-to-san-francisco</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="section"></h1>

<p>It’s been three months since I first moved to San Francisco and decided
I should share why I moved here in the first place. The primary reasons
why I moved to San Francisco are for my career and to be around more
like-minded people.</p>

<p>Career-wise, what made San Francisco appealing to me is the number and
diversity of employment opportunities. In Connecticut, if you want to
work with “technology” then you work for one of the many insurance
companies headquartered there or an agency of some kind. In addition to
available opportunities, there is also more parity between the job
market in the bay area and my skill set and experience. For example,
today <a href="http://www.indeed.com/">Indeed.com</a> reports 184 results for the “Python” in the entire
state of Connecticut, while there are nearly 2,700 results for the San
Francisco Bay Area. At one point in my life, I was told I was wasting my
life messing around with GNU/Linux and other Open Source software.
Things would have been a little better if I moved two hours away to
either Boston or New York, but if I’m going to move then I might as well
get better weather out of it, too.</p>

<p>I also moved to San Francisco to be around more like-minded people.
Things that interest me (besides gardening and home brewing) are
startups and tech. There were a few groups around my old location that
were interesting, but they typically required an hour long drive to show
up to their events. Often times, the groups failed early due to a lack
of participation (including the hackerspace I founded but that story is
for another day).</p>

<h2 id="thoughts-so-far">Thoughts so far</h2>

<p>As I mentioned, I’ve now been here for three months. My thoughts so far
are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The place really is quite small. Especially in tech. Everyone seems to
know everyone, which can be fun socially, but you need to watch what
you say when you’re talking shop.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Sillicon Valley/SF Bay tech isolation chamber is real (and so is
the echo chamber). Companies sometimes seem huge when you’re in the
bay, but if you talk to anyone from outside of the area, they’re like
“<em>Who?</em>”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>San Francisco’s neighborhoods are really awesome. SF
is divided into a bunch of small neighborhoods, each with their own
unique attributes. There really is a place for everyone.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I moved to San Francisco because I thought it would be good for my
career and because I thought I would meet more like-minded people. This
has certainly proved to be the case. What I was not expecting but have
experienced so far is how small and isolated the SF tech scene actually
is.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
